hey there everyone ramesh here welcome
to angular spring boot full stack
application development course
this is going to be three hours full
coding course guys
in this course you are going to learn
how to build a complete single page web
application using angular and spring
boot
okay
in this course i am going to use angular
you can use angular 8 or 9 or angular 1
as per your project requirement but i am
going to use angular 10 in this course
all right so whatever angular version
you use you can use you know
but make sure that you will update
angular version uh in
you know a package.json file
okay so while creating angular project i
will show you uh where you can exactly
update the angular version
all right guys so this is going to be a
complete series or a course for
developing a full stack web application
using angular and spring boot
in this tutorial series we will learn
how to develop crude full stack web
application that is basic employee
management application using angular 10
and springboard
basically we are going to develop five
features in this
project
so we will create
create employee feature list and fly
feature update employee feature delete
employee feature and we view employee
feature so these are the five features
we are going to develop
in our employee management application
and we are going to use spring boot to
develop restful web services and angular
to develop client-side application
so before
uh you know implementing our employee
management application that is full
stack application let's quickly have a
demo what exactly we are going to build
in this tutorial series
so this is the user interface of our pro
stack application that is employee
management application
so this is the employees list page here
we're gonna add implies
and this is the header of our
application this is a footer and header
you can see here employees list tab and
this is add employee tab
let's go ahead and let's click on add
employee tab and this is the create
employee page
and we're going to use this page to add
a new employee to the employees list
let's go ahead and let's add one of the
employee
first name ramesh last name federi and
email id ramesh gmail.com hit submit
yeah here we go
my employee is added to the employee
list let's go ahead and let's add one
more employee let's say john cena and
email id as john gmail.com hit submit
let's go ahead and let's add one more
employee let's say admin
and last name admin and email id
let's say
admin gmail.com
yeah here we go so we have added three
employees to the employee list now let's
go ahead and let's see
update
functionality i'm going to update ramesh
43 employee
click on update button and here i'm
going to update first name from ramesh
to ram
and email id from ramesh2ram
gmail.com hit submit button yeah here we
go
alright guys look at here the employee
successfully updated
now let's go ahead and let's delete one
of the employee let's say i'm going to
delete john cena employee click on
delete button
yeah
so employee successfully deleted now
let's see one more employee
i'm going to delete ram employee yeah
great so here we have details button you
can click on details button to view a
particular employee details
in a separate page
and here we have back to employee list
button
click on this button to navigate to the
employ list page
so these are the five features that we
are going to develop in this project
add employee
list employee
and delete update and
view details employee so these are the
five functionalities that we are going
to develop in this full stack
application
let's take a quick overview of angular
and springboard
angular is a platform and framework for
building single page client applications
using html and typescript
angular is
written in typescript
okay and you should
have basic understanding of typescript
in order to work with angular and we are
going to use angular 10 which is the
latest release of angular as up now
well angular is
a popular especially for developing
single page applications
angular is module modular in nature so
angular application is divided into
multiple models and each module can have
internal components services directives
templates etc
and angular provides the built-in
features like defendant injection and
data binding
alright so angular is one of the most
popular typescape based framework for
building single page applications
well springboot is
pretty much popular
for developing a restful web services
and micro services
spring boot has taken spring framework
to the next level it has drastically
reduced the configuration and setup time
required for spring based projects
you can set up spring project with
almost zero configuration and start
building the things that actually matter
to your application
angular and spring boot is a great
combination to develop full stack
application
what you will learn in this tutorial
series you will learn how to develop
crude full stack application with
angular as front end and spring boot as
a back end
and you will learn how to build a great
restful apis with spring boot
you will learn how to solve the
challenges of connecting angular
front-end to rest api which is developed
using springboard
you will learn how to connect a rest api
to jpa or hibernate with springboard so
basically we are going to use spring
data jpa which in turn uses hibernate as
a gpa provider so you will learn how to
use ping data jpa or hypernet in
springboard application
you will learn how to use wide variety
of spring boot starter project such as
springboot
web starter dependency springboot data
jp dependency
and
other dependencies so we are going to
use mysql database so you will also
learn how to connect springboot
application with mysql database
and you will learn the basics of angular
like angular modules components data
binding and routing so while developing
this
angular application i'm going to also
explain you about
angular modules components data bindings
and routing as well
now let's take a look at client server
architecture at the server side we have
springboard application
which creates and exposes rest api and
at the client side we have angular
application which we use to develop
single page application and it consumes
a rest apis which is exposed by
springboard application
all right so this is how
the client server architecture looks
like
let's take a look at our angular
springboard crew full stack application
architecture basically we are going to
develop two projects spring boot project
at the backend and angular project at
the front end
well
let's first take a look at our
springboard application architecture and
then we'll move on to the angular
application architecture
so at the springboot architecture we
have different components like spring
rest controller spring data jpa
so at a persistence layer we are going
to use spring data jpa
and spring data jp it will communicate
with a database that is mysql so we are
going to use mysql database in this
series
so spring data jpeg it internally uses
hybernet as a jpi provider and it will
expose
all the database operations for a
particular entity
so for example we are going to create
employee jp entity in our project
and spring data jpa provides all the
crude operations for employee entity so
we use spring data jp to reduce a lot of
ballet fluid code that is required to
develop a persistence layer
and here spring rest controller we
develop using spring amuc to
develop and expose rest endpoints and we
are going to develop five rest apis
for employee resource
so this is a simple architecture of our
springboot project
at a database layer we are going to use
mysql database but you are free to use
any relational databases like postgres
database
sql server oracle etc because spring
data jp internally uses hibernate ibn
out of the box hibernate supports all
the relational databases so we just need
to change the configuration and
underlying code remains same
in case of hibernate so you are free to
use any relational databases
so let's take a look at angular
application architecture so look at here
we have different components in angular
application we have view templates
components services and we may have a
direct use pipes etc
so we use html to develop templates
and components basically contains a
properties and methods so which will
hand which will handle the data for
templates
and we we can perform two-way binding
between template and component
so basically
we use angular interpolation to bind a
properties in templates
components will basically handle a user
interface data
services are angular services
where we keep all the common logic and
we inject services in required
components using angular
dependency injection
and in our application
we write all the rest client code in
services to make a restfa call
well angular has its own http model so
we can use http model to make a rest api
call
okay
great so this is the simple architecture
of our angular springboard crude
poolstack application now let's quickly
take a look at what are the tools and
technologies that we'll be using at the
front-end side we're going to use
angular 10 which is a latest release of
angular while recording this video
and we are going to use typescript to
write a you know a code in an angular
application and we are going to use
node.js and npm
and we use visual studio code id to
develop angular application and we are
going to use angular cli to generate
angular application its components
services classes and lot more things
and we are going to use bootstrap for
css library to make our angular
application
uh stylish and responsive
next let's take a look at the tools and
technologies that we'll be using at the
server side we're going to use spring
boot 2 plus
and spring data jpa internally uses
hibernate
and we're going to use marvin 3.2 plus
and we use jdk 1.8
and we're going to use embedded tomcat
8.5 plus
and we use mysql database
well these are the tools and technology
that we'll be using at the server side
now let's take a look at preview widgets
for this
course
so you should have basic knowledge of
html and css
and you should have
basic knowledge of typescript
if you know javascript already then
probably you will understand typescript
very easily
make sure that you have installed
node.js and npm on your machine
and you should you should know the basic
fundamentals of angular because i am not
going to cover angular fundamentals or
basics
so make sure that you have enough
knowledge of angular
to develop this full stack application
and also you have enough knowledge of
springboot to develop our full stack
application
now let's understand the project
development process
so we'll basically develop five
functionalities and we'll begin with
list employee functionality and then
create employee functionality and then
update employer functionality next we'll
develop
delete employee functionality and
finally we develop
we apply functionality
so in this order we'll first begin with
list employee functionality and then
create update delete and view okay
let's open eclipse sds id and let's
quickly create a springboot project
in eclipse sds id go to the file section
new and then choose
spring starter project
so look at here this is the spring
initializer
website url and spring initializer is
integrated in eclipse sdsid and we can
use pre-initializer to quickly create
and bootstrap spring-based project
let's give a name to the project like
springboot backend
and keep type as marvin packaging as a
jar java version 8 along with java
let's give group id as net.java gates
and artifact id is same as the name of
the project
and keep version and description as it
is
and keep package as net.java guides dot
springboard but you can give any package
name that you want once you are happy
with project details
click next
and here
we have spring boot version that is
2.3.1 so this is this is the latest
release of spring boot as of now
now what we'll do we'll pick up spring
boot starter dependencies
let's go ahead and let's pick up spring
web starter dependency
we use spring web starter dependency to
develop additional web services
and let's go ahead and let's pick up
spring
data
gpa dependency
so we use playing data jp dependency to
develop a repository layer and spring
data jp internally uses hibernate as a
jpi provider
we basically use bing data jpa to reduce
a lot of boilerplate code that is
required to develop a dowel layer all
right and we're going to use mysql
database so let's quickly
pick up mysql jdbc driver
and let's also choose
spring boot dev tool dependency
spring boot
dev tools dependency so we use this
dependency because whenever we make some
changes in a project we no need to
restart the server again and again okay
all right guys once you select all the
required dependencies hit finish
this will create
a springboard project in eclipse sds id
yeah here we go
once we have created springbook project
let's go ahead and let's create a
database
open mysql workbench and just type sql
statement like
create
database followed by name of the
database
let's give name of the database ads
employee
management underscore
system
something like this
and execute this sql statement
and refresh here and look at here the
employee management system database is
get created
once we create a database let's go ahead
and let's configure mysql gdbc url
username password in springboot project
go to the resource folder within a
resource folder open
application.properties file
and here just type
spring
dot
data source
dot url
okay
let's give jdbc url to connect to the
mysql database
so we get here we have
employee management system database that
just we have created in mysql workbench
similarly let's go ahead and let's
configure
username and password
let's type the property
spring dot
data source
dot
username
it's root
let's also
configure
password
it's again root
okay so make sure that you will change
julius url username password as per your
uh you know mysql database installation
on your machine
now let's go ahead and let's configure
hibernate properties
we are going to we are using mysql
database so
we have to
configure
hibernate dialect for mysql database so
look at here this is a property and this
is the value
so we are using mysql file
dialet
okay now let's go ahead and let's
configure one more hybrid property
so look at here so this is a hybernet
detail auto property so use this
property to automatically create the
tables in a database so i haven't it
will automatically create a
tables in a database with no need to
manually create the tables
all right guys
once we configure jdbc credentials and
hibernate properties
let's go ahead and let's create a
packaging structure
right click on root package
new and then choose
package and let's queue package name as
model
let's create one more package right
click on root package new and then
choose package
and let's give package name as
controller
again let's go ahead and let's create
one more package
let's name it as
a repository
alright so let's go ahead and create one
more package and let's name it as
exception
all right
let's go ahead and let's create a jpeg
entity
right click on model package new and
then choose class
let's give
identity name as
employee
all right
let's quickly define
instance variables
private
long id
private string first name
private string last name
and
private string
email id
all right let's quickly create get a set
of methods to access these private
fields
and also create
a parameterized constructor
right click source generate constructor
using fields
deselect id and
hit generate and let's also create a
default constructor
so remember whenever you create a
parameterized constructor you have to
create a default constructor because
hibernate internally uses proxies
to create
uh you know proxy objects
all right once we have created employee
class now let's go ahead and let's use
jp annotations
to map
uh you know uh
this model
to the relational database table
let's go ahead and let's use add rate
entity annotation
and let's also use add rate table
annotation to provide a table name
let's give table name as
employees
all right let's define a primary key for
our
table let's use add id annotation and
also let's
use a generation
primary key generation strategy for that
let's use add generator value annotation
and it has a property called strategy
and let's use generation type as
identity
and let's use accurate column annotation
to provide a column name to the field
here basically we map a column name to
the field and we can also give a column
name over here
let's use a name attribute to provide a
column name
let's say first
underscore name
and let's copy this
and similarly give a
column name to the last name
last underscore name and also
your column name to the email id email
underscore id that's it guys
that is pretty much we have created
employee jp entity now what we'll do
we'll create a
repository interface
right click on repository package
new and then choose
interface
here let's give a
repository name as
employee
repository
great now what we'll do will extend this
interface
from
jpa repository
so jp repository basically exposes
database code methods
like
save find by id find or delete by id
delete
okay it exposes a lot of methods
and it provides
out of the box implementation for all
the database methods so we don't need to
write any
binder plate code that is required to
you know
develop the dow layer
let's pass
employee jp entity and here
the type of the primary key
let's annotate this interface with
accurate
repository annotation
all right
so look at here
jp repository provides a lot of methods
like find all
and also it provides a sorting
support
okay and
also
provides a pagination so look at here it
internally extends paging and sorting
repository paging and sorting repository
base provides support for sorting and
pagination
and
paging and sorting repository extends
code repository so code repository
interface exposes all the
crude methods
for
entity okay for example save
save all find by ide
exists by id
okay
so
jpa repository internally extends all
these interfaces so
we can leverage all these methods
we don't need to create
methods over here
okay great
now it's time to create
a restful web services
so before that let's go ahead and let's
create one custom exception
class
right click on exception package new and
then choose class let's name this custom
exception class as
a resource not found exception
so whenever a resource not exist in a
database then we can throw this
exception
okay from the api layer
rest api basically
uh you know throws this exception that
we will see a bit later
this exception extends
runtime exception
okay
and
runtime exception internally implements
serializable interface so let's go ahead
and let's
quickly add the
serial version id here
let's
say public
and here let's
pass string message
and we simply
pass this message
to the
super class
okay it's pretty simple
custom exception
now let's annotate
this
exception class with add the red
response status i rotation
use value property
and let us say http status
not phone
okay
so basically we use this custom
exception so whenever a record not exist
in database then rest api will throw
this exception and
we have annotated this exception with
address response status annotation so
api will return a not found status to
the client
okay that's
great
now let's go ahead and let's create
spring muc controller right click on
controller package new and then choose
class and let's call controller class as
employee
controller
okay within a controller we create a
rest api so let's add
at the rate
press controller annotation
and also add address request mapping
annotation
and let's define
a standard url over here slash api
slash version v1 so this is the standard
we use typically
whenever we develop our http is like v1
like version one so we are releasing all
the rest apis
as a release one
and this is the api so this is a
standard uh
url endpoint that typically we use in
our https okay
now let's go ahead and let's
inject
uh employee repository over here
employee repository
and let's add at the rate
at world annotation
to inject this repository by spring
container
now
we'll develop
get
all employees
arrested api
just type public
and then list
so this rest api should return a list of
employees to the client so let's give
return type as list of employees
let's give a method name as
get all
employees
all right and just
return empire repository
dot
find out method so look at here find out
method returns a list of employees okay
let's select this
and let's add
at the rate
get mapping annotation
and let's specify a url here slash
impulse
okay so once we hit a url in a browser
like localhost 8080 api slash v1 slash
employees then this rest api will get
called and this api returns a list of
employees to the client
alright let's go ahead and let's
run the springbook project and let us
test this rest api
open our springboot main class right
click and run as springboot app
all right guys our spring boot
application is up and running on
embedded tomcat server on port 8080
and look at here we haven't created
create employee rest api in order to
create a records in a database
we have directly created get all
employees so what we'll do we'll insert
some records in our employees table in a
database and we call this rest api and
will retrieve this api will review all
the employees from the table and it will
return to the client
okay
let's go back to the
mysql workbench and let's insert few
records
now if you refresh
the schemas and if you look at here
employees management system
database implies table is
created okay so this table is
automatically created by hybernet
and now
right click and select rows so if you
look at the
table there are no
records
in a table so let's quickly insert few
one
email id
parameter
gmail.com first name
ramesh last name
and
also is insert one more record
tony at the
gmail.com
first name tony last name
stark
let's keep these two records and hit
apply
and finish
all right
let's execute the select statement again
in order to make sure that the records
are there in a table
yeah we have two records in a table now
let's go back to the browser and let's
hit a rest api in a browser tab and
we'll be able to get a
response as a json array of employees
objects
okay great
all right guys open the browser
go to the new tab and just type
localhost 8080 slash api
slash v1 slash
employees
and hit enter
yeah here we go
we got a json
array
json array as a response from the rest
api
we can use
postman rest client to test our get all
employees rest api so open a postman
client and
in a
enter request uh you'll just type
localhost
8080 api slash women slash employees and
select http get method
all right and hit send
button and here you can see
we got a
json response
we got an array of employer objects
hey guys it's time to create angular
application
so before creating angular application
make sure that you have installed
node.js and npm on your machine
so in order to install node.js what you
can do is you can just type node.js in
browser
hit finish
and head over to the node.js
official website so it will navigate to
the official website of
node.js on download page so so this is
the download page of node.js official
website
from here you can
download a latest list of node.js
go ahead and download a latest list of
node.js and install on your machine
so when you install node.js it will
automatically install npm so you no need
to manually install npm again
well let us check the version of node.js
and npm that we have installed
in our machine
so for that let's go ahead and let's
open
a command prompt so i'm using windows so
i can use a command prompt here but if
you are using linux or ubuntu you can
just use a terminal
to check
a version of node.js just type the
command node hyphen v so this will
tell you the version of node.js that you
are using and in order to check the
version of npm just type the command npm
hyphen v
so this will give you
the version of
npm that you are install in your machine
all right guys once we have we have
installed node.js and npm
let's go ahead and let's install angular
cli
if you are unaware with angular cli so
angular cli is a command line interface
tool which we can use to create angular
applications
so it's pretty awesome too that follows
the best practices to create application
structure
file structure naming conventions for
components component templates services
directives a lot of things
all right guys we are going to use
angular cli to create and setup angular
application and we also use angular cli
to create a components
services classes and a lot of things
let's head over to the browser and let's
search for angular cli
open new tab in a browser and just
search for angular cli and head over to
the angular cl official website and look
at here these are the commands you can
use to
you know install angular cli i have to
create angular project and run the
angular project so these are the couple
of commands you can use to quickly
install angular cli and create angular
project and run angular project
okay
so if you want to know more about these
commands you can read the description
over here
all right let's go ahead and let's use
this command to install angular cli
you can just copy this command and head
over to the command prompt paste it here
so this command will install angular cli
globally
well i have already installed angular
clr in my machine so what i will do is i
will just check
the version of
angular cli just enter the command ng
iphone iphone
version
so once you install angular cli in our
machine you can use this command to
check
the version of angular cli that you are
installed in your machine
all right guys
so look at here once the command
completes you can able to see
angular cli 10.0.7 here this is the
version of angular cli that i am right
now using
and you can able to also see the node.js
version here
all right guys
all right guys once we have installed
node.js npm and angular cli
we're gonna need a vs code id to develop
angular application for that just search
for vs code download in a browser and
hit finish and head over to the download
page of vs code
official website
and this is the download page so from
here we can download you know vs code
ide installer if you are using windows
then check out this
button
and if you are using mac then check out
this button so just click on this button
you will be able to download
vs code installer
once you have installed vs code id in
your machine
then we are good to
create
angular application and
we are good to develop angular
application
all right great
so go to the file system and create a
folder something like angular spring
boot crude full stack app
and open this folder in a command prompt
all right and just type the command code
and dot
so this will open
a vs code id inside this folder
hit enter
i hope you guys are following the steps
yeah great
now within this folder we are going to
create our angular application
well
we are going to use integrated terminal
of vs code
so in order to get an integrated
terminal go to the terminal tab here
click on new new terminal
and at the bottom you can able to see
here
a terminal is opened
well
in order to create
angular application we are going to use
command
that is
new
ng new followed by name of the project
so this is the command which we can use
to
create angular app
once we create angular app we can use
the command ng server to run angular app
well go to the integrated terminal and
just type the command emg
new followed by name of the project so
i'm going to give name of the project as
angular
front end
you can do any project name that you are
happy with but i am going to give a
project name as angular front-end
all right hit enter
so
this will ask you few options
would you like to add angular routing
yes
which
style sheet format would you like to use
so i'm going to use default that is css
so don't choose any option just hit
enter
and this command take couple of minutes
to install packages
it will basically create
node underscore models package and it
will install all the packages and
necessary stuff
once the command completes it says
packages installed successfully
and you can able to see
angular hyphen front-end folder is
created
and if you expand this folder you can
able to see
a whole lot of files and folders are
created inside this
angular hyphen front-end folder so this
is our angular application and this is
the folder structure that is created by
angular cli
so before knowing few of the important
files and folders let's go ahead and
let's first run our angular application
go to the integrator manual and just
type the command cd
and then navigate to and navigate inside
the folder that is angular hyphen front
end
hit enter
so before running angular application
using ng server command make sure that
you are inside
a folder okay and just type the command
ng
so hit finish
so this will basically run angular
application in local development server
on port 4200
once ng server command completes it says
confired successfully
all right and angular live development
server is listening on localhost 4200
let's go ahead and let's open the
browser and hit this url in a browser to
access our angular application
go to the browser and in a new tab just
type
a localhost
yeah here it is so this is the default
as you know template provided by angular
so this template or html page contains
few links which will in turn navigate to
the
angular official website documentation
angular clr documentation and angular
blog site
alright
alright guys our angular application is
up and running on port 4200 let's go
ahead and let's explore important
folders and files in our angular app
generated by angular cli let's begin
with package.json file
so package.json file contains the name
of the project version of the project
and a few scripts
to run angular application to build
angular application and to test angular
application and this is the dependency
section inside a dependency section we
define all the dependencies
and its version required to run our
angular application so notice here we
are using angular 10 which is latest
list of
angular and look at here we are using
dev dependencies
so basically package.json file contains
all the tools libraries and packages
which are required to run our angular
application
and package.json file which which looks
like um palm.xml in my own project
so whenever we use the command npm
install it will install all the
dependencies and its version in node
underscore modules folder likewise in
marvin project so palm.xml contains all
the dependencies and plugin sites so
whenever we run the command like marvin
install
maven
clean install then
basically marvin will download all the
dependencies from the internet and it
will store in a local repository
so similarly
when we run the command npm install so
node.js will basically
download and install all these
dependencies in node underscore modules
folder
alright so this is all about
package.json
and we have
tsconfig.json
file so this file
related to typescript configuration
and it internally
called
tsconfig.app.json
and ts config.spec.json
well
so we write a typescript code in angular
application right and browser don't
understand the typescript so these are
the few typescript configuration files
that will that will convert a typescript
code into javascript so that browser can
able to compile and run the angular
application
so next is node underscore models folder
so this folder contains all the
dependencies packages that are required
to run angular application
and this folder will basically generate
when we
uh create our angular app using angular
cli
and whenever we use npm command to
install any javascript libraries or
packages
so these labeling packages are will get
you know stored in this local folder
that is node underscore modules folder
next is src folder so all your
development goes inside src folder
within a such folder
you can find
file so this is a very important file
and this is the entry point of our
angular application
next is index.html file so this is a
single file which will get served in a
browser and we are developing single
page application so we should have only
one
html file and it in turn update uh the
same html file so look at here app root
so this is the selector which we have
configured in app component
and this selector in turn
get call
app component html template
okay great
next is
app module so app module is a root
module of our application and inside
this model we configure
you know components in declare
declarations array and other modules
dependent modules inside imports array
and we configure providers like services
and within a app module we bootstrap and
kickstart app component and app
component is our
root component
well angular application can have
any number of modules but it should have
at least one module and that is called
app module or root model
okay
and angular application can have any
number of components but it should have
at least one component that is called a
root component or app component
understood
and next is uh
folly fields so this is related to
browser uh uh specific uh to support
different browsers so this file will
uh you know take care and styles.css so
here we basically globally uh you know
configure css files
and this is a test.ts file which is
related to test cases in angular
application and this environments folder
so all the environments uh
you know configurations goes inside this
folder
and assets folder contains a static
files like images uh
javascript files css files etc
and this is the app routing modules
uh we basically configure a routing of
our angular application so this is a
pretty much about
uh i know the files and the important
files in our angular application
now let's see how the control flows in
our angular application so look at your
main.ts file so this is the entry point
of our angular application and the
control first comes to the main dock and
main dot ts file in turn
bootstrap and kickstart app model using
bootstrap model method
and app module in turn bootstrap and
kickstart app component app component is
our root component and aqua app
component has a property called title
and this title will be you know rendered
inside
app component html template so it's this
is how the control flows in
angular application
let's go ahead and let's understand what
are the components that we are going to
develop going forward in our angular
application
well
we are going to create four components
and each component
represents
a functionality for example create
employee component we develop to perform
create employee functionality
we create employee list component to
perform employees functionality we
create update employee component to
perform update employee functionality
and we create
employee details component to perform
view employee details functionality so
each component represents
a you know separate functionality
okay great
now we have
employee service so employee service is
basically a angular service which holds
all the
http rest client code
and basically we use angular service
to you know to keep all the common logic
and we can inject employee service in
required components so basically we use
angular dependency injection to inject
angular services in various components
and we can delegate a task to the
employee service for example we can keep
all the logging
uh common logic in employee service and
we can inject in required components and
we can call
you know logging methods
so in our angular application we create
employee service
class
which will communicate with server using
a rest apis
and
so employee service internally uses http
client module to make rsd pay call so
basically we are going to
make a get a rest api call
and post the rest api call
and put rusty pay call
and delete rest api call so these are
the
crude operations right so we are going
to write a rest client code in employee
service to make
this rest api call
okay great
and look at here we have a router so we
are going to configure
routing in app routing model
angular provides its own
routing model so we can use angular
provided modules
to configure routing in our angular
application
all right great
and also we are going to create a
employee
employee model
so this is basically a typescript class
it contains a properties
and we create this employee typescript
class model to hold a response of the
rest apis so going forward we'll create
all these components service and we
configure routing in our angular
application
so basically we will begin with employee
list component but before that
we are going to integrate bootstrap 4
css library in our angular application
in next video
we'll integrate bootstrap for css
library in our angular application so
that we can make our angular application
responsive and stylish
so once we integrate bootstrap css labor
in our angular application next we'll
start creating employee list component
and then
once we complete employees component
then we'll start creating a create
employee component and once we complete
create employee component end to end
then we'll start update employee
component so once we complete update
employee component then we'll
create employee details component to
perform view employee details
functionality
alright guys this is the quick summary
of our angular application that we are
going to develop going forward
let's go ahead and let's add bootstrap
css library in our angular application
bootstrap is a css
framework which we can use to develop a
responsive layouts in our web
applications
so there are various ways to integrate
bootstrap in our angular application we
will see a few of the simple ways
so first we'll
see
how to install bootstrap using npm
command and we'll add a path to our
angular application
for example
open new integrated terminal in vs code
go to the terminal click on new terminal
and make sure that you are in a root
folder of your project
and here you need to just type the
command npm install bootstrap hypernyp
and save
and hit enter
so this will install a bootstrap css
packages inside
a node underscore modules
folder and it will add a new entry in
package.json file
with its version for example if you open
for package.json file here you can see
a booster package is added once
bootstrap css package is successfully
installed
go to the angular.json file
and here you can find
you know styles
array so here you can configure
a bootstrap css
you know library like this so this is
the path to
the bootstrap css library that just we
have
installed
so this is the first way
and
the second way is
go to the
styles.css file and here we can
just import
uh the path of the bootstrap css library
that just we have installed so this is
pretty simple and i prefer using this
way
i globally define the css
file path over here inside stall
styles.css file
and another way is you can download
bootstrap css
uh you know remote links from
cdn for example go to the browser and in
a new tab just search for
bootstrap for cdn link
and go to the official website of
bootstrap
and here you can find the cdn remote
links of bootstrap css library
go ahead and click on copy button so
this will copy
this url
so comment out this code
and go to the index.html file and go to
the header section
within a header section just paste the
link
okay so this is the another way
so these are the three ways uh
i have found you know integrating
bootstrap css library in angular
application so you can use either one to
integrate bootstrap in you know angular
application
so to keep it simple i am going to use
the cdn remote links like this
or you can also use uh this way so this
is the
standard way that i prefer so let me
do this
and let me use
this way
so you can go to the styles.css and you
can configure this path like this
and in order to make sure that
whether the bootstrap is successfully
integrated in our angular application
what i will do is i will
open app component
template and i will just remove all the
code and i will add some
css to h1 html element like this
let me use a double curly braces though
this is called
uh interpolation in angular so we can
use antifullation to access the
properties of component
and title is defined in app component so
i am going to just display title in a
web page
and let's use text center bootstrap css
class in order to
i know display this title at the center
of the page
let's go ahead and let's use class
property and here i'm going to say text
hyphen
center
let's save the file and let's go back to
the browser
and let's
let's refresh and you can able to see
here
angular front end so this is the name of
the project that is
the title that is printed on a
middle of the page it means that a
bootstrap css library is successfully
indicated in angular application
if you comment out this code
all right
and save the file
and look at here
so without a bootstrap css library how
the title aligned here
okay you got the difference right
so look at here after adding bootstrap
css library
the title is aligned at the center of
the page
all right guys we have successfully
integrated bootstrap css library in our
you know angular application going
forward we are going to use a lot of
bookshare css classes
to make our web pages responsive
and uh you know pretty
we are going to create employee list
component
which will display a list of employees
on a web page
all right
before that let's recap what we have
done so far
we have created springbrook project we
have created jp entity and jpeg
repository
we have created and exposed
list employee rest api
we have created angular application and
we had a quick overview of angular
application
and in previous video we have added
bootstrap 4 in our angular application
in this video we will create typescript
class for employee
so we create a employee typescript class
which will hold a response of list
employee rest api and we also create
angular list component
angular least employee component to
display a list of employees on a web
page
in next video we'll connect our angular
application with least employer rest api
and
we will get
a list of employees from list employee
rest api and we populate a list of
employees on our web page
alright guys
let's go ahead and let's create
typescript class for employee and
we'll also create angular list employee
component
let's switch to the vs code id and let's
create typescript class using angular
cli
make sure that
you are in a project that is a root
folder or project angular iphone front
end
and let's go ahead and let's use angular
cli to create typescript class
let's use the command
ng
g g for generate and then class
and name of the class
let's say employee
so this command will create a typescript
class
hit enter
so this command created
two files employ.ts and employ.spec.ts
well
expand app folder within app folder you
can see these two files are created all
right
so let's go ahead and let's define some
properties in our employee typescript
class
so basically we are creating employee
typescript class which will basically
hold a response of a rest api
okay
let's go and let's define some of the
properties
id
so the type of the id is
number so in typescript we have number
as
a type
and then
define first name
property and this should be string
last name
this should be string
and then
email id
and again this should be stream it's
pretty simple and
these properties should match
the jpa employee entity that we have
created in our springboard project
all right
great
now let's go ahead and let's create
employee list component
we are going to use angular cli to
generate employee list component
go to the integrated terminal
and make sure that you are in a
root folder of your project
and just type the command
ng
and then g for generate
c for component and let's type name of
the component
let's say
employee hyphen list
hit enter
so notice here this command created four
files
and
also updated one of the file that is
app.module.ts file
well if you go to the apps folder
expand app folder and expand
employee hyphen list folder so this
command created employee list folder and
within a folder it has created four
files and it also updated
app.module.ts file
okay
so
angular cli will take care to update
newly created
component in app model
so we no need to explicitly add a newly
created component
in declaration section of app model
okay so look at here we just created
employee list component right and
angular cli will automatically added
employees component to the declarations
array and this component belong to
this model
so as i mentioned earlier each module
have multiple components
and we can have as many as models in our
angular application
well
so look at here inside a employee list
folder we have four files
this is the employees component dot css
file this is a component private css
file which will applicable to employee
list component template
this is employees component template
it has some default text which is
provided by angular cli
and this is the employees component
which will basically handle the data and
it will process the data
and this is
the employee list component test class
so this is related to test cases and we
are not going to focus on test cases in
this series
so let's get in let's open employees
component.ts file so it has employees
component basically this is a typescript
class which is annotated with add
component
decorator
so look at here basically add component
decorator that marks this type
typescript class as angular component
and provides the configuration metadata
that determines how the component should
be processed
intensity and used at a runtime
all right and at the right component
decorator has three attributes selector
template url and style urls
so we use selector as a custom html
element
and this selector will be replaced with
this employee list component
template at a runtime
and this empowers component.css file
this is a component css private file
which will only applicable to
employees component.html file
now what we'll do let's go ahead and
let's copy this selector
and let's open
app component
template
and here
we're going to use a selector as
custom html html element like this
and if you save the file and
if you go back to the browser
we will be able to see our employee list
works
text printed on a web page
okay
so look at here
employees component template has
employee list works
paragraph so this is the paragraph
printed on a web page
now we can
we can you know add a html code to
display a list of employees
on our web page
so let's go ahead and let's
create a html template which will
display a list of employees on a web
page
let's replace this default
content
and let's go ahead and let's
add html code here
i'm going to create h2
html element and let's say
employee list so this is
the header upload page
and then i'm going to create a table
and let's add a bootstrap css classes
to the table
table and then table stupid
table header
inside table header let's go ahead and
let's create a table uh
a row here
and inside our
row we are going to create
column
let's say first name
employee first name
and this is employee last name
and similarly let's create one more
column
and this is gonna
employ email id
okay pretty simple and let's create a
table body
inside a table body let's use a table
for row here
and then
inside a table row
we're going to use
ng for
inbuilt angular directive to iterate
over a list of employees
so look at here this is the important
step
let's use star ing
for so this is
the inbuilt angular derivative which we
can use to iterate over a area of
elements or a list of elements
so ng4 which works similar to for loops
which we use in programming languages
like in java c c plus plus etc
but the difference is ng for directive
we use to
iterate over html
elements so in this case we are going to
iterate over a table row
if we have 10 elements in an array
then ng for direct you will
create a 10
uh you know html elements
all right that will see once we
create once we write this code
okay and here
within a double quote let's create a
variable
javascript variable let
and then employee
of
employees
okay so implies basically this is an
array which we need to define in a
component
so go to the employee list component
and here we are going to define
a property called employees and this is
the type of employee array
and make sure make sure that you import
employee typescript class
at the top
import
and then employee
from
employee
okay great
so once we define employees
you know property in our employee list
component and this property we can
access
in employee list component template
using ng directory like this
now
we are iterating our employees
array now let's go ahead and let's use
a td html element here
and then use double curly basis
so this is called
interpolation in angular so we can use
interpolation to access properties from
object
in our case we have
employee
and then let's go ahead and let's
call property
of the employee object like first name
so look at here
the array type so the array type we have
a employee right
so this employee class has properties id
first name last name and email id
so we are using these properties to
access employee first name last name
email id all right so here
so just we have called first name
similarly
let's go ahead and let's
use
a last name employee last name
last name property let's call
email id
okay
great
let's save the files and let's go back
to the browser
yeah here we go the html table is
looking good
and the bootstrap css classes are also
successfully added to the html
table
now what we will do we will add some
dummy data to the table and in next
video we will make a step a call and
will populate our htp response data in a
table
let's open employees component and
inside
in the init method we are going to add
few records to the employees array
so look at here this is employees array
and we have added two objects employee
objects to the employee array
well let's save the file and let's go
back to the browser
and look at here
we can able to see two employees are
displayed in html
table
well let's go ahead and let's add some
bootstrap css class like container to
the do
so that we can align this table
in a proper format
let's open
app component
template
and here
let's go ahead and let's create
our view
let's add a bootstrap css class
that is a container
and let's enclose
this
app employee list uh you know element
inside you and let's save the file and
let's see how
the table looks in the browser so look
at here now our
html table looks good
right
all right guys
in next video we will make a sdk call
and we'll populate a real data
on a
table
in previous video we have created
employees component which will display a
list of employees
on a web page like this and we have
created some dummy data and we have
populated a dummy data on a web page
in this video we are going to create a
angular service which will make in turn
a rest api call and will populate a sdp
response data
on a web page
all right so before implementing
angular service in our angular
application let's quickly have a
overview of angular service
we use angular service to share the data
among various components in angular
application
sometimes we want to write a similar
piece of code in various components
so instead of repeating same code in
various components in angular
application
we can keep as you know common code in
an angular service and we can inject
that angular service in required
components so that we can reuse the same
code
so to achieve this we can use angular
and angular provides a dependency
injection feature
so dependency injection feature make the
testing and debugging very simple
a component can delegate certain tasks
to the services such as fetching data
from the server validating user input or
logging
directly to the console
so validating user input and logging so
these are the common code which required
to
reuse in different components so this
common code we can
write in angular service and we can
inject that service in various
components to call
these services
and
inside angular service we can write a
rest client code which in turn make a
sdp call
and we can inject angular service in
angular component so that angular
component can delegate
i know this task like fetching data from
the server to the service
now service is responsible to fetch the
data from the server
well to define a class as a service in
angular
we use add injectable decorator to
provide the metadata that allows angular
to inject into a component as a
dependency
all right
so
we'll see about i will see more about
add injectable decorator once we create
angular service in our angular
application
so look at here
in this video we are going to create
angular service
which in turn use http client module to
make a restfa call and we inject
employee service in different components
and different components will call
a methods of employee service
all right guys let's go ahead and let's
create employee service in our angular
application
so switch to the integrated terminal
and make sure that you are in a root
folder of your application
and let's use angular cli to generate
angular service
just type the command
ng
and g g for generate s for service
followed by name of the service
let's give a service as employee
hit enter
so this command created two files
all right if you expand app folder
within app folder you can see
employee.service.tsignemploy.service.spec.ts
so these are the two files created by
this command angular cli command
go ahead and click on
employee.service.ts and look at here
this is the employee service so
basically this is the typescript class
which is annotated with add injectable
decorator
so this at injectable decorator marks
this typescript class
as a you know
as a provider and it can be injected
into various components
all right and this service is provided
at a root level
now let's go ahead and let's use
http client model to make rsd pay call
so before that make sure that your
spring boot application is up and
running and you are able to access
arrest endpoints
let's go ahead and let's
access one of the rest api
in a browser just type
localhost.js api slash v1 slash
employees so this will
gives you a area of employees as a
response
well our application is up and running
and we can able to access the you know
employee list rest api
now let's go ahead and let's use http
client
module
to call this rest endpoint
so just follow the steps so first step
is go to the app module
and app module use depends on http
client module in order to use http
client
here just type
http
client module
all right and make sure that http client
module is imported at the top
just type the
statement import
within a curly basis http client model
from
at angular
slash common slash
http
alright so http client module is present
in package
angular slash command slash http
alright so this is the first step so
make sure that we import http line model
in imports array of
app model
now second step is
go ahead and inject http client in
employee service
so go back to the employee service again
and here in constructor we are going to
inject http client
module
private
and then http client
and this is http client
and make sure that we import http client
from the angular package
and let's go ahead and let's
import http client at the top
http client
from
it should be from
angular package angular
slash command slash http
great
now we have imported http client module
and we have injected
in employee service using constructor
now let's go ahead and let define the
property here
private and let's say base url
and we are going to define a base url
for our rest endpoints
go to the browser and just copy this url
so this is going to be a base url of all
the crude rest apis
copy and paste here
and save the file
let's go ahead and let's create a method
let's say get
employees list
followed by colon and just call
observable
so make sure that observable
you know imported from rxjs library
at the top
and then we need to provide a type here
type is rep employees
because this rest endpoint you know api
returns
a rap employee object so for that
we need to
pass
employee array like this
now let's go ahead and let's return
this dot
http client
and then call get so we're going to make
a get
a request type for that we are going to
call get method
and we are going to pass a parameter to
the get method that is base url
so look at here
we need to
use a backstick here not a single quote
okay
and then
dollar
within the currently basis
this dot
base url
okay
and here uh the return type is
employee array right so let's just pass
this
up employee to the get method like this
yeah here we go
so this looks good right
so this is observable
and we are going to subscribe for this
observable object in component
if you look at the documentation of get
method
so get method basically you know
it constructs a get request that
interfaces the body as a json
object and returns
the response body in the given type
and if you look at the return type of
the get method it returns observable
of the http response
okay
it returns basically observable
object
now let's go back to the
component employees component
and let's go and let's inject employee
service and employ this component
go to the constructor and here type
private
and then
employ service
employee service
and make sure that we import employee
service at the top
import
within the curry basis
empire service
from
okay so once we inject employee service
in employees component
we can call employee service methods
so in previous video we have created
submit dummy data right here inside
ngoninit method so let's go ahead and
delete this data
and let's create a method here this dot
get employees
okay
and just
define this method here
let's say
private
get employees
and here we are going to call
employee service
and then get employee list method
so this method returns observable object
right so we can go ahead and we can
subscribe to this
method so basically it does asynchronous
call
and this subscribe will call once it get
the data
and
to the subscribe method we are going to
handle the resp you know response of the
rest api
and data
followed by
error syntax and here
we're gonna assign a response to the
employees
it's property simple right
so this is the response data and we
assign this response data to the
employees property so this employees
property is
our app employee objects
all right
guys let's save the file and let's go
back to the browser and let's see
whether
we get a successful response from the
server or not
here if you refresh you can see here
admin
youth employee is successfully populated
on the employee list page
so this is the rest api that we have
invoked from the angular service
and same response we have printed on a
table
now open mysql workbench and let's add a
few more records to the table so that
we'll see few more records in a web page
let's say id 30 and
first name ramesh
so this is the email id right
programmatic
gmail.com first name ramesh
last name
birthday
and id 31
email id
c9 gmail.com
first name john
last name cena
and apply
apply and finish
okay
let's go back to the browser
and let's go ahead and let's refresh
and here we go
so i mentioned john so these are the two
employees we have just inserted in
database
and the same employees record we have
successfully got from the rest api and
we have populated on a web page
all right guys we have successfully
created a list employee
feature
hey guys
we have completed end-to-end list
employee functionality
in this video we are going to configure
routing and navigation in our angular
application
well going forward we will be creating a
lot of components in our angular
application
and hence in this video let's go ahead
and let's configure routing and
navigation in our angular application
all right
so configuring and you know routing and
navigation is pretty simple in angular
project you just
follow the steps i am going to implement
in this video
well
when we create angular application using
angular cli command like ng new followed
by name of the project so this command
will ask a question for us like would
you like to add angular routing
so if we have a requirement uh you know
to configure routing in our angular app
then we say s
otherwise we say no all right
let's say we want to configure routing
in our angular application and we say
yes
then angular cli will automatically
configure routing for us
and we need to only configure routes
that are required to navigate to
specific
url path to specific component
so that we will see a bit later
if you don't
specify
an angular routing option here
if you say no for this question then you
need to manually configure routing step
by step
and let's go and let's understand what
are the required steps required to
configure routing in angular application
first step is open index.html and here
inside
header
tab you can find a base tag
base href equals to slash
so this base tag is required
so that the application knows how to
construct the urls while navigation
so this is the first step
and second step is
you need to create approaching.module.ts
so we have already you know configured
routing using angular cli so angular cli
already created
all the necessary steps that are
required to configure routing in angular
application
but
if you don't configure
routing while application creation using
angular cli command like engineer then
you need to manually configure routing
like this so first step is you need to
you know provide base tag
in index.html like this and second
second step is you need to create
approaching.module.ts file like this
and we
create a app routing model
and it is annotated with add ng module
decorator and here we specify a router
model from
angular slash router package
and router model has a method
for routes and forward method takes
routes as an array
and so look at here we have defined a
constant routes array and inside array
we configure routes and each route we
configure as an object
all right and this route is type of
routes a model which is from
angular
router package
all right so this is the second step
and the third step is
go to the app
module.ts file and here you can see app
routing model
so you need to import
app routing module and you need to
provide app routing model
inside imports array
so that our application needs to know we
have configured routing in our angular
application
all right so this is the third step
and fourth step is we need to configure
routing in our app routing model
so here inside routes array we need to
define our routes
all right
inside routes array
let's create a javascript object
and
so
a router definition is a javascript
object
here i will define a path
so path in our case is
employees
and then
component
component is
employees component
all right
so look at here
this route
is a definition of javascript object
okay and each route
typically has two properties
first property is path
so it's a string
and it specifies the url path for the
route
and second property is component
it specifies what component your
application needs to display for this
particular path
it's pretty simple right
now let's go ahead and let's configure
one more route
so
we need to compute the route to redirect
url from empty part to slash employees
so let's go ahead and let's configure
route to redirect from empty
empty path to
employees
okay
let me show you how to do it
let's create a javascript object inside
an array
and this is path
and path is empty
and then we have redirect
to property
this should be
employed
and then we need to define
a path
match so this should be
a full
all right
so when we enter a empty path in browser
like localhost 4200 it should redirect
to employees
a path and employees
path
has a component like employee list
component and this is the path match
strategy
so it is recommended to use path match
full strategy when we configure
a empty path
all right so this is a pretty simple
routes we have defined
in routes array and these routes are a
we pass to
for root method of router module
and this router module
we we get from
angular slash router package
it's pretty simple right you understood
the flow right
so first we configure base
tag
with href equals to slash in index.html
and then
we create app routing model and inside
app routing model we provide we import
router module from angular slash router
package
and this
model has forward method and we pass
routes to this forward method
and then we
we import app routing model inside our
root model that is app model
here so this is third step
and we configure routes in our routes
array in
app routing model
so this is the post step
and fifth step is we need to configure a
router outlet
directive
so go to the app component dot
html template and here we have provided
app employee list selector as a custom
html element so let's replace this with
the directory called
router
router outlet
so router
outlet is angular provided directly
okay so we need to use this directive in
order to update our templates to
dynamically load a component based on
the
url path
let's save all the files let's go back
to the browser and let's verify how our
routing works
so if you type the url local host port
to double zero
it should redirect
to the employees path so look at here
when i enter localhost port double zero
it is redirecting to
slash employees
so this is what we have we have provided
route here
so when we type
empty path then it should redirect to
the employees and the corresponding
component that is employed component
will get rendered
okay
great and when we use the url path
localhost 4200 slash implies this should
render the employee list component
all right guys we have successfully
configured routing in our angular
application
now let's go ahead and let's
see how the navigation we can configure
currently our application supports two
routes right
however only way to use these routes is
for the users to manually type the url
path in the browser's address bar
but sometimes we want to click on some
link or button then we should
you know navigate to the corresponding
component this is called the navigation
and let's see how to configure
navigation
in our angular application
so open app component
template
and now what we'll do will
implement header and putter for our
application and also will provide a
navigation links
in header section
okay for that let's go ahead and let's
first
write the code for the header
this is the
navigation tag and here we're going to
add some booster css classes
okay
and inside this navigation bar
will configure the urls
and provide a bootstrap css class like
this
so this is the unorder list
so let's also define a list here
and let's go ahead and let's provide a
bootstrap css class that is navigate now
hyphen item
and let's go and let's configure
hyperlink here
and bootstrap css class
like
now link
and then
let's
say employee list
so once we click on this hyperlink that
is employee list we should be able to
navigate to the employee list
page
now let's use a angular directive that
is
router link
to provide a navigation path url path
here for example
a router link so router link is a
angular provided directive and here we
provide
a url path so this is the employees so
that we have configured
in app routing model here
all right so this is the angular
directive that will basically
connects the routes to a specified
template files
okay
now we want to identify the active route
right so for that we can use angular
directive called router link active so
we can use this directive
to identify the active route
and this active
is basically provided by
bootstrap so we can use active class
here
so this is a simple header
and here i have just added a single link
so going forward we'll add few more
links to our header section now let's go
ahead and let's add a folder footer
section to our angular application
let's write a code here just use footer
html element
and the css class
let's say porter so this is the custom
css class that will
you know add a style to this css class
bit later
and inside putter we're going to add a
new here
and let's add a bootstrap css class that
is container
and inside of you
let's specify
spam
and inside spam let's write the text
like all writes result 2020 at java
guides
it's a pretty simple footer
let's open
styles.css file and inside this file
let's create a porter css class
with some
you know css properties like position
absolute
width hundred percent height 70 pixel
background color blue
text align center color white
okay let's save all the files and let's
go back to the browser and let's see how
it looks
yeah here we go
so look at here our angular application
looks good now
so let me recap what we have done in
this video we have configured routing
for our angular application
for example if we enter a url localhost
4200 it should redirect to slash
employees url
and we have
added header with some navigation links
and we have also added footer to our
angular application
let's create
add employee rest api open employee
controller
and here just let me write the comment
create employee
rest api
all right just create a method first
public
and employ
so this rest api returns a employer
object as a json so let's keep empower
as a return type
and the name of the method is
create employee
and just pass employee
object as a method argument
okay
and this
method returns
employee object right so let's call
employee repository dot save method so
save method return
i employ object
so let's pass employee
object as a method argument to the same
method
now we have created a method okay let's
use
annotations to make this method as a
rest endpoint
let's use at the read
post mapping annotation so this method
will handle
http post request hence we are going to
use at the red post mapping annotation
and let's configure url over here slash
employees
and
post the request contains a json
request body right
and json request party we are going to
directly map to the employee object so
let's use that
for that let's use address
request body annotation
that's it guys very simple
rest api
now what we'll do we'll start the
tomcat server that is we will just run
our springbook project and we will test
create employee rest api using postman
dress client
now look at here our springboard
application is up and running our
embedded tomcat server on port zero
edurate zero now let's go back to the
post managed client
and let us
test the api
so look at here
the http method is post
and this is the rest endpoint url
localhost eight zero zero slash api
slash v1 slash employees
and in a header just type content type
as application slash json and in the
body select raw and
give a json
request
uh you know a body like this
first name thumb last name cruise email
id thomadder gmail.gmail.com
hit send button
so look at here
we got a successful response with http
status 200
okay
all right guys we have successfully
stored a recording to a database let's
go ahead and let's verify
open mysql workbench and just
execute select query on employees table
so look at here a new record is
successfully inserted into a database
all right
now what we'll do we'll add one more
record
let's give post name as
amir
and last name as
khan
and
email as
amir gmail.com and hit send button
so look at here we got a response
and let's verify a record in a database
table
here we go so look at here record is
added to the database
it's pretty simple
all right
great we have successfully created add
employee rest ap
so we are going to create create
employee component
and we are going to create create
employee form
through which
we can add a employee
all right before that
let's quickly
uh you know look into the two-way
binding
all right consider we have a form with
first name last name email id and
similarly here we have a component class
it has a property employee so employee
is basically a typescript class it
contains the properties first name last
name and email id
so when we create the employee property
of employee typescript class in
component we access its properties in
html template using
employee.firstnameemploy.lastnameemploy.email
this
whenever i enter something in first name
last name and email id input controls
then the corresponding properties will
get automatically updated in component
class
and whenever i do some changes in model
properties in component class then the
corresponding properties will get
updated in html template
so this is how the two-way works in
angular
so look at here here we have data
binding and event binding
so whenever we define properties in
component class and we bind that
properties in
component template then it is called
property binding or
data binding so we basically use angular
interpolation to bind a properties in
html template
and when we perform some
events on html template it should be
bind in component class using of methods
or functions
so angular provides a nice feature that
is two-way binding and angular also
provides ng model directive so we can
use ng model direct to to achieve
two-way binding in our angular
application set door to a vs code id and
let's quickly create a component
so make sure that you are in a project
a root folder a project angular hyphen
front end and just type the angular cli
command
ng
g for generate
c for component and just followed by the
name of the component let's say create
employee
hit
enter when this command completes it
created four files and app model is also
updated
well if you expand app folder within app
folder you can see here create employee
folder is
created and within a create employee
folder four files are generated
and if you open app model
angular cli has automatically added
create employee component to
declarations array
all right
now let's go ahead and let's configure
route for our newly created component
that is create employee component
let's go ahead and let's open
app routing model
module and here we're going to configure
a route
so let's go ahead and let's
create a javascript object within a
routes array
let's specify path
and then
let's say
create employee
as our path
followed by
components property
so once we
enter a path like create hyphen employee
then corresponding component will get
rendered
so the component name is
create employee component
it's pretty simple right
so once we configure route
now we can able to
provide
a links in the header section of our
angular application let's open app
component template
and here we are going to configure
a link for add employee
page
so let's go ahead and let's copy this
list and paste it here
and let's change the link name
accordingly
so this is
going to be our
create employee or let's say
add employee
link and here we are going to change a
router link
create employee
so this is the path that we have
configured in a route
here
okay
let's save the file and let's go back to
browser
and here you can able to see
add employee link is added in a header
section if you click on add employee you
should able to navigate to create
employee
path
all right so our
routing is perfectly working
if you click on employee list it should
navigate to the employees list page and
if you click on add employee to navigate
to create employee page
let me summarize what we have done in
this video we had a quick look on two
way binding in angular so basically we
are going to use ng model directive to
achieve two-way binding in our angular
application
and we have created create
employee component and we have added a
route to create employee component and
we have also added add employee
a link in a header section so that once
we click on add employee it should
navigate to create employee
page
in next video we'll create a form that
is create empire form through which we
can add a new employee to the employees
list
now let's open create employee component
and let's
define a property
that is employee
of type
employee
class
and we are going to create object of
employee class
and initially all the properties of the
should be emt
all right
let's head over to create employ
component template and let's design a
form here
let me replace the default code
and let me write
the title of the
page using s3 tag here
and let's say
create
your employee
and after that let's go ahead and let's
create a form
and inside the form here
we are going to use ng submit
event to listen
you know form submission event
well look at the syntax here
within a parenthesis
we have
ng
submit
and let's assign
a event handler to this ng submit event
let's say
on submit
all right so this is the ng submit event
which is enclosed in parenthesis
and we have assigned a event handler to
this
event and this event handler will define
in component class
let's
open create employee component
and here we're gonna
define
an unsubmitted
function like this
let's go back to create employee
component
and let's use a bootstrap
css classes to design our create empire
form
let's create a new with class
and then add bootstrap css class that is
form hyphen group
after that create a label
and let's give name to the label like
first name
and after that
create a input field
input
type as text
and then
add bootstrap css class
form hypercontrol and then id equals to
first name
and then we're gonna use eng model
directive for two-way binding
so look at the syntax here
ng
model
and enclose
ng mod directive in parenthesis
and after that enclose this in square
brackets
okay so this is the syntax to use ng
directive in input
element
and let's assign a property to this
directive
let's say employee
dot
first name
so this is the employee we have defined
in a component
and employee property is of type
employee and this is the first name last
name you may like so these are the
properties of employee class that we are
using in the form
all right next
give a name to the input element like
first name
it's pretty simple right
so the important point here is eng model
so this is the directory that we are we
are using for two-way binding so as soon
as we enter something in this input text
the corresponding property will get
updated and as soon as we update this
property in component class then this
input text box will get updated
well let's go ahead and let's
add
this input text box to the last name and
email id as well let me copy this do and
paste it here and let me change
the necessary stuff
this is the last name
and id should be last name
just copy this
and name should be last name and
property
employee dot
last name
well let me again copy this and let's
define for email id let me change the
label
this should be
email
id
let's go ahead and change the id here
this should be an email id
and name email id and property
employee dot email id
and just save the file
and let's
add a button here
so when we enter
or something in these
input text fields then we need to submit
the form right for that we are going to
create a button over here
and then let's add a boost of css class
like button button success and the type
of the button is
submit
and let's give name to the button as
let's save all the files and let's head
over to the browser and let's see
whether it is working or not so look at
here
we got a error
it says like can't bind to ng model
directive since it is not a known
property of input
well ng model directive is you know
present in a separate package
in a separate model that is forms model
so in order to use ng module directive
we have to import forms module in our
app module
all right
let's head over to the vs code id again
and go to the app model
and here
we're gonna import
forms model
from
angular
forms
and just copy the name of the model
and here after http client model just
paste it here
let's save the file and let's head over
to the browser so look at here the error
is resolved
so remember whenever you want to use ng
model directory you have to import forms
module in app model
okay great
so look at here the form is scattered so
let's go and let's align this form
properly
go to the create employee component
template and let's go ahead and let's
add a new here
video and add a bootstrap css class like
column
mid and
let's say it and let's add offset
offset boost of css class like offset
mid
and then define theory
and let's
close this due at the end
save the file
and let's go back to the browser and
look at here
we have successfully aligned our form at
the center not properly at the center so
let's
let's go and let's change the css class
again let's change from
column 8 to 6 and let's save the file
and let's go back to the browser yeah
now the form aligned at the center
all right great now go to the create
employ component and here what we'll do
we'll just
put some
logs here and just we're going to print
m4 object to the console
let's use this keyword to access the
properties
let's save the file and let's go back to
the browser
and now what we'll do we'll enter from
data and we submit the form data and
we'll able to see the form data will be
available in
on submit
a method
so let's enter first name ramen's last
name for the email id remix at the
gmail.com
and let me go to the dev tools of chrome
browser
go to the console here and just clear
the console
and then
hit submit button
and let's see yeah here we go the
employee object is successfully printed
on a console with proper data
post name is last name for the email id
remember gmail.com
all right guys great
now the form data is available in on
submit method
in next video we'll make a htp call to
send this form data to the server and
that the server
rest api will process this data and it
will store in a mysql database
in previous video we have created create
employee form and once we submit
this form
we are able to get a form data inside
on submit
method so here we have create employee
component right and we have defined earn
submit method inside create employee
component so once we submit the data the
form data will be available inside this
method so look at here we just uh
provided console log and we have printed
employee object to the console
in this video we will make a rest api
call and we'll send the form data to the
rest api and rest api internally will
process
uh this request and it will you know
save the employee from data in a mysql
database
so first we need to create a method
inside employee
service
so here we're gonna create a method
which will make a restrip a call and
we'll send the data from data through
htp and http internally store data into
mysql database
all right guys let's go ahead and let's
create a method let's say
create employee
and let's pass a employee
object as an argument to create employee
method and this is the type of
employee typescript class followed by
colon
followed by
observable
and here we're going to pass
object
as a type or you can pass any so if you
don't know the response of the hdb you
can just pass object or any uh type okay
like this
all right let me provide object here
and return
this dot
then http client and then we are going
to send a
http post request like for that we are
going to call a post method here
and then backstick
let's use dollar and then curly braces
and just call
base url
okay a comma just pass employee object
that's it
it's pretty simple right
so this is the first request so we have
to send the data in a body of the post
method like this
now we'll head over to the component and
we'll make this
method call over there
so basically we inject employee service
in a create employee component and we'll
call
employee service method
all right great let's head over to
create employee component
and let's inject
using constructor
let's say
employee service
and this is employee service
and make sure that employee service is
imported at the top
okay
great
now what we'll do we'll create
a save employee method here
and inside save employee method
let's call this dot employee service and
then call its method that is create
employee and let's pass
employee object as a method argument
to this method
and this method returns observable so we
can subscribe this
method so that we can process a
synchronous response here
and it has
the data as a response object and arrow
syntax and we can able to
print the error
response like this and here i'm gonna
just
print the success response to the
console
data so once we submit the employee form
successfully then we should be able to
navigate to the employees list page act
for that
we are going to use a router here
so i'm going to create a separate method
let's say
go to
employee list
and here let's use a router to navigate
to the
employees page
let's first inject a router from
angular
you know router package go to the
constructor
and here let's
inject
a router and make sure that router
should be imported from
angular slash router package
okay now we can use this router to
navigate to the corresponding
uh path
so here i'm going to use router
this dot router dot navigate and then we
pass the path of the route that we want
to navigate
so router provides a navigate method
and through navigate method we can pass
a path
to which we are going to navigate now we
call this save employee method from on
submit
let's go ahead and let's
call
this dot
save employee method
from on submit method
let's go ahead and let's add
employee information and submit the form
let's say i'm going to add a employee
like
uh let's say
ram
and
power and email id as ramadra gm.com hit
submit
i guess we got some error let me see
what is the error
inspect and go to the console
we got a success response but uh we are
not able to navigate to the
employees page
okay so let me head over to the vs code
id and let me see what is missing
yeah here we go so basically we need to
call this method from
here
this dot
let's call go to employee list
method
and save the file and let's see how it
works now
uh let me go to the employees list
and let me
add one more employee now
let's say
for a bus
and then
let's say jado
email id as
prabhas at the rate gmail.com hit submit
so look at here bus employee is added to
the employee list it means that we have
successfully made a sdp call and we have
successfully stored i employ from data
into mysql database and we were
successfully able to navigate to the
employee list page
all right great so let me update this
title
let me head over to the
vs code id again and go to the app
component.ts file and here this is the
name of the angular project so let me
update this
to
let's say angular
springboard
code
full stack app something like this
and let's save the file and let's head
over to the browser
and you can able to see the title is
updated
angular 10 spring boot cool full stack
app
now our application looks good
so let me summarize what we have done in
this video
we have created create employee method
which in turn make a rest a call and we
have
you know pass the employee from data to
the rest api
and we inject
employee service in create employee
component
and we use its method that is create
employee method and we pass employee
form object to the client employee
method
and we process the response and we also
just printed
a error object if there are any
exception in
you know processing this request so
after a success response of the rest api
we navigate to the
list employee page using
uh you know router here
okay it's pretty simple
all right guys uh we completed
you know create employee functionality
end-to-end
in next video we'll create a few rest
apis and then we'll create update
employee component to perform update
employee functionality
get
employee by id rest api
get employee
by id rest api
okay
just type a method
public
and this
method returns
ample object
to the client so let's give a return
type as employee
and let's view method name as
get employee
by id
all right
and we are going to pass
id as
a method argument right
long id
let's annotate this
method with at the rate
and get mapping annotation
let's configure the rest endpoint url
over here
employees slash
id
okay so this is the path variable
now we want to
map or we want to store this id value
into
you know the java variable so for that
we are going to use at the right path
variable annotation to map this id
with this variable
so let's use
add the rate
path variable annotation
now let's retrieve a ampulla object from
the database for that we are going to
use
employee repository
let's create employee
object here
and let's use
the employee repository
and we're going to call
find by id right find your d method
and just fast id id to the find by
method
so look at here find by id returns
optional
as a
written type
so here what we'll do we'll use at the
air dot
orioles throw method so if record not
existing database then
we are going to throw resource not from
the exception for that
let's use orioles throw
method over here
and
basically we need to
pass a lambda expression to this method
because this method internally uses
uh
functional interfaces
okay and we use lambda expression to
implement a functional interface
let's use lambda expression syntax here
and just pass
object of
the custom exception that is resource
not found exception
a resource
not found exception and just pass the
custom message over here
employee
not exist
with
id
then just pass the id over here
let me break this statement
okay great
so what we have done
we have we have called find by id method
so this method basically returns
optional
uh object as written type and optional
provides or else throw method so if we
record not existing database then we
just simply throw resource not from the
exception like this
now let's return
a employee
object
to the client
so what we'll do we need to also return
http status right for that we need to
use a response entity
class
let's use return type as
response
entity and this is the generic class so
let's type
let's pass employee as a generic type
and here let's return
response entity
and we are going to
return our case status that is 200
status so let's choose ok and just pass
the empire object in a body
that's it
it's pretty simple right
right guys this is pretty simple uh rest
api that is
uh you know get employed by idealist api
now let's go ahead and let's test this
rest api
for that what we will do i will start
the application
go to the spring boot application main
class
right click run as spring boot app
now look at here springboard application
is up and running on embedded tomcat
server on 4080
now let's go back to the postmodernist
client and let us test this rest api
open
a new tab
and just type
localhost address slash api slash v1
slash employees
and here
we are going to retrieve a particular
employee
so let's go back to the
database so i am going to get a employee
ramesh with id 1
so let's pass id 1
as a path variable
slash 1
and choose http get method over here and
simply hit send button
so this will retrieve a employee object
with ide 1.
if you want to retrieve employee with id
2 just pass id 2 over here and just hit
send button so this will retrieve my
employee with id 2. alright guys we have
successfully created
get employee by id rest api and we have
tested
using postman rest client
now let's create
update employers dpi
go to the employee controller
within employee controller
let me just write the comment here
update
employee arrest api
okay
so just follow the steps
public
and
response entity and
just pass type as employee
and let's give a method name as
update
employee
okay
make this
e as caps
and we are going to pass
id as a method argument
along with that
the object of the employee
class
so basically client sends updated
employee object in a request body for
that we are going to
use
employee object here
now what we will do we will use
annotations over here so let's use both
mapping annotation
for update operation
so this method will basically handles a
put request
for that we're going to use at the
report mapping annotation
let's configure rest endpoint url over
here
slash
implies
slash just fast
path variable here that is id
now let's map this path variable with
the java variable by using at the rate
path variable annotation
and also we are going to
directly map
a request json object into a java object
for that we are going to use at the rate
request body annotation
pretty simple right
great
so to update i employ first we need to
retrieve
our existing employee from the database
for that what we will do we will reuse
this code just copy this code
so this will basically
you know retrieve employee by id if
employee is not existing database then
it simply throws resource not found
exception
so look at here this is the
duplicate local variable employee here
just pass
this as
let's rename this
object as
employee
details
now what we do will update this
retrieved employee object with
a request employee object okay
just
change the first name
employee details
dot get first name
similarly
let's also change last name
employee details
dot get
last name
employee
dot
set email id and let's get a email id
from the
employer details object
and
set to the object
now once we set all the
information that we want to update to
the employee object we simply save the
sample object to the database
let's go ahead and let's save
this updated employee object to the
database
let's use save method and just pass
employee object as a method argument
and here
we store
the updated employee object in a
separate employee variable and we simply
return
this object to the client
for that just use return
response entity
dot okay
so this is 200 status and in a body just
type
updated employee
all right that is pretty much
so what we have done we have retrieved
our employee from the database and we
have added all the
updated information to the employee
object and we have stored that tempo
object into a database and we have just
written updated employee object to the
client very simple rest api
now let's run the spring project and
let's test this rest api using postman
rash client
alright guys springboard application is
running on tonka's server on port 8080
let's go back to the post manage client
go to the new tab
and just type localhost
h0 api slash v1 slash employees and this
is the update rest api so select
put http
method
and go to the header
and we are sending json as
a request body right so for that let's
use content type
as application slash json
and i can go back to the body in a body
where you're sending
a json right
so let me copy the json object from the
post request and let me paste in a body
and
what we'll do is simply update a
employee that is a remiss employee let
me show you that go back to the
my circle work point so look at here
this is the table it has four record we
are going to update the employee with id
one okay that is a ramesh employee
so let's pass
id here to the
url as a path variable
and i am going to update a first name
from remiss to rom
and last name from pathetic to
something like jado
an email id from ramishadra
gmail.com or i'm at the right gmail.com
so look at here first name is remix last
name for 33 email id i mentioned
gmail.com right so i am going to update
these details
with these details okay so once you
configure all the details hit send
button
yeah here we go so look at here the
response we got a updated record in a
response and we have successfully
updated first name last name and email
address
let's verify in a
table so let's
uh let's query the select statement here
so look at your record first record is
get successfully updated
all right guys we have successfully
created updated rest api and we also
tested it using post management
well
in this video we create update employee
component and we'll configure route for
update employee component and we create
a update button
correspond to each employee once we
click on update button it should
navigate to the update employ page let's
head over to the visual studio code id
and let's create
update empire component
go to the integrated terminal make sure
that you are in a root folder of our
angular application that is angular
hyphen front end and let's go ahead and
let's type the command
ng
g4 generate c4 component and then
followed by name of the component that
is
update hyphen
employee
hit enter
once the command completes it created
four files and updated app module
right
so if you go to the app folder within
app folder
update m5 folder is created
and within update employee four files
are generated all right
and angular cli will automatically add
a newly created component to app model
so we no need to explicitly add a newly
created component to app model
okay
now once we created update template
component let's go ahead and let's
configure a route for update employee
component
open app routing module
and go to the routes array within the
routes array create a object
and we have path property
and let's give
a path as update
employee
and then slash
colon
id so we are going to update a
particular employee right so this id
represents the particular employee id
okay and we basically pass this id to
the rest api to get a particular
employee from the
rest api
well
after that we have a component property
and here
we specify the particular component name
that is
updated by component
so whenever we hit this url in browser
the corresponding component will get
rendered
so this is a very simple routing for
update employee component
now let's go ahead and let's add update
button
so we'll add update button corresponding
to each employee so that whenever we
click on update button we'll name we'll
able to navigate to the update employee
page
let's open
the employee list
component template
and here
we have a table right and let's create
actions column first
actions
under actions column we have
a table right we have a button
let's
create a button over here
so inside a button we handle a click
event
so this is the syntax of
angular to bind a click event to the
button
and then here we specify event handler
in our case we have
update
to employee event handler
and then within a parenthesis we provide
id we pass the id
all right pretty simple
followed by let's add a bootleg css
class
like button button info
and then give a name to the button like
update
now we'll define this
event handler
in
our employee list component
here so once we click on button it
should navigate to the update employee
page right so let's go ahead and let's
define this
event handler here and we are going to
use a router to route
this request to the update employee page
for that let's go ahead and let's inject
a router here
private
router
and make sure that a router is imported
from
the package angular slash router
okay
now let's go ahead and let's use this
router here
this dot
router dot
navigate
and update employee
event handler
should have id right
so look at here this id we have passed
in a button
this is the id right
okay
so to the navigate method we're going to
pass a array of
elements so first is
the path
path of the route that is update
employee
followed by
id
so update iphone employee so this is the
route that we have defined in app
routing component right here
so this is the syntax
uh you know to
call update empire page
using a router
it's pretty simple
now let's go ahead and let's uh
test this from the browser
so look at here update button is
appear
correspond to each employee
and once we click on update button
it is
navigating to
update employee page and look at here
the route
this is the route we have configured
right so update hyphen employee slash
2929 is id of particular employee
and this is the update employee page
now let's go back to the vs squad id and
let's design update employee page
in previous one of the video we have
created
uh you know
create employee form right and i have
explained you step by step how to design
a create employee form
and update employee form which uh which
looks similar to a create employee form
so let me just copy the whole
whole content of create employee
component.html page
and let's
open update employee component.html and
here i'm going to just paste it
and let's go and exchange accordingly so
let's change a page title from create
employee to update employee
well
you can use a single component to
perform create and update functionality
but to keep it simple i am going to use
separate update employee component to
perform update employee functionality
well
so this is the input field to handle
first name and this is the input field
to handle last name and this is input
build to a handle
employ a email id and this is the button
let's save the file and let's go back to
browser and let's see how this page
looks like
yeah here we go
update employee page
once i click on update button it should
navigate to the update empire page and
this is how the update employee page
looks like
well create employee and update employee
page both looks
same
and yes so you can use the same
component to perform both operations but
to keep it simple i have created a
separate update employee component to
perform update employee functionality
well in case of update we need to
populate
a particular employee data
in the form so that user can able to
update the employee right
so basically we
make a get employee by id sdpa call and
we pass this id to the rest api rest api
basically uh you know fetch the
particular employee by id from the
database and it will send that employee
data employee data in a response and we
populate that response employee data in
the update employee page
well in next video we'll make a get
employee by id rest api call
and we'll fetch a particular employee by
id
and then we populate that employee
in the
update employee page so that user can
able to update that particular employee
in previous video we have created update
empire component and we have configured
route for update employee component and
we have added
update button correspond to each
employee in employee list page and once
we click on update button
it should navigate to the update employ
page and we have also designed update
employee
form
in this video we'll make get employed by
id rest api and we populate that
particular employee
in the update employee form so that user
can able to update
the employee all right let's go ahead
and let's write the code
to make a rest api call
and we populate the response of the rest
api in the update employee page
let's head over to the vs code id
let's open
employee service and here we're gonna
write a rest client code which will make
a get employed by id rest api call
let's give a method name as get employee
by id something like this
and then we need to pass id to this
method and this is the type of number
followed by
observable
and then
we know that this this rest api returns
a employee object so let's go and let's
pass
a employee
employee model as a type to the
observable
class like
employee
and then just simply return
this dot
http client
and then call a get method
so we are making a get http request
right
and then we know that this rest api
returns empty object so let's go ahead
and let's pass employee
model as a type
followed by let's pass a parameters to
get method
notice here we are using backstick
within a backstick
we use dollar within the curly braces
we're gonna use this dot base url
followed by
slash
dollar
and within a currently basis just pass
the id
that's it
it's pretty simple right
now i'm gonna call this method from the
update employee component
well let's go and let's first inject
employee service
in update employee component
open up the template component and go to
the constructor just in inject
empire service over here
and make sure that employee service is
imported at the top
and let's go let's create an employer
property
employee
equals to
new employee
here we're going to make
a method call here employee service and
then get employee id
so look at here this is important
so get empire by id
method expects
uh id right
and we need to retrieve id from the
route
so let me show you how to do it
we'll use activated route
model
to retrieve id from the route
for example
in a browser you can just search for
activity route
in angular
and go to the activated route api
so basically activated route provides
access to information about a route
associated with a component that is
loaded in an outlet
and this activated route
provides a couple of methods like couple
of properties snapshot and params so we
use these properties to access id from
particular route
let's first
you know inject
activated route
private
let's call it as
route and then activated route
and make sure that activated route
should be imported from angular slash
router
and we're gonna use
a route here
so first i will create a property here
id
id should be a type of number
and then here i am going to assign
id from route to id property here
let's use this dot route
and then we have snapshot
and then we have parents pass the key
here to get
id value
that's it so this is how we get id from
particular route
using this syntax
so we use activated route it has
snapshot and parents properties
and we use these properties to access id
from the route
well now we can able to get id and we
can pass this id here
all right and just subscribe to this
method so it returns observable so we
can subscribe to it
and then handle the response data here
data arrow syntax
and then just assign data to the
employee property here
this dot employee equals to data
and here
we can also handle error response we
just print the error response here
like this
okay great and this employ property we
have used in
update employee page here
employee dot first name employee dot
last name and employee dot email id
well as soon as this employee
property is populated with data that
data will be reflected in the form
now let's save all the files and let's
go back to the browser and let's see how
it works
yeah here we go
the browser automatically refresh and it
internally made a get employee by direct
api and it will populated employee data
in the update employee
page
it means that we have successfully made
a get employee by direct api and we have
populated the response of get employed
by idealist api in update employee page
so let's go back to the employee list
page and if i click on update button of
particular employee let's say ramesh
employee
here here we go
the employee particular employee data is
you know updated successfully on update
employ page
now user can able to update the first
name last name
and email id and once user sub hit turn
submit button
we again make a sd pay call that is
update employees tp call we submit this
updated employee from data to the rest
api rest api internally store this data
into mysql database
so in next video we will make update
employees tpa call and will send this
updated employee form data to the rest
api and rest api will internally store
this data into mysql database all right
guys
in previous video we have made
get employee by id rest api and we have
populated a particular employee data in
update employee page
in this video we will make a update
employer sdp call and will send update
employee from data to the update
employee rest api and update employee
sdp internally store this update
employee data into mysql database
let's go ahead and let's write arrest
client code to make update employees dpi
let's head over to vs code id and let's
open
employee service
and here we are going to create a method
let's say update
employee
and this method takes two parameters
one is id of the particular employee
and second argument as
employee
updated data
and this is the type of
employee typescript class
followed by
colon and then observable
and here we can pass
object as a type
and then
we simply return
this dot
http client
and then this is a put http request so
let's call put method
and
use backstick
and dollar within a curly basis let's
call base url
and then
slash
and then dollar and let's access id
using
dollar curly braces like this
and let's pass second
argument as employee object that's it
guys
pretty simple
now i'm going to call this update
employee method
in update employee component let's head
over to the update template component
here
and we have update employee form right
and once we submit the update and
platform it will you know call
on submit
event handler so let's first
define this on submit event handler in
update employee component here
within our unsubmitted method
we're going to call
user service
and then we call
update empire method of user service
object
and update employee method expect two
arguments one is id and another is
employee object
so let's go ahead and let's pass id here
so ide how can we get id and we can get
id like this this dot id
comma this dot
employee
so this id we already got from the route
using this syntax
and
this is the employee object right
and this employee object will
automatically populated
by
angular using ng model directive
and we're gonna subscribe to this method
because if this method uh
returns observable
so we can subscribe and we can handle
those synchronous response
and followed by
handle a response inside subscribe
method like this
zero syntax
so once
employee updated successfully and we got
a success response from the rest api
then we'll navigate to the employee list
page right
so for that we need to write a route
here so that we should navigate to the
employee list page
so go to the create employee component
and here we have already written a code
let me just reuse this code
just copy and go to the again
update employee component paste it here
and first we need to inject a router
here
inside a constructor
private
router and then it's a router so make
sure that router is imported at the top
all right and we use navigate method of
router and then we pass
a path a particular route
which it navigate
okay for example this is the path we
have configured in app
routing model
this is and it will
render a corresponding component that is
employee list component
now let's go ahead and let's call this
method
here this dot
go to employee list
and here we can
handle
the error response like we can print
the error response to the console
all right pretty simple right
so we just call update employee method
of employee service class
and then we pass id and updated employee
object to the update employee method
and this is our synchronous call so it
returns observable so we subscribe to it
and we can handle the response
asynchronously and once we got success
response from the rest api we can call
you know uh
go to employee list method right
internally
uh you know it or it will route to the
employees page
well let's see all the files and let's
go back to browser and let's see how it
works
well
go to the employee list
page
let's go ahead and let's update one of
the employee i'm going to update admin
employee
click on update button and let's update
first name
from admin to
administrator
and email id from admin to administrator
and hit submit button
yeah here we go the employee is
successfully updated
the first name and email id is
successfully updated right
all right guys
we have successfully made update
employer hdpa call and we have sent
updated employee form data to the
updated employee rest api and employee
html internally store this data into a
mysql database
or guys we have successfully implemented
update employee functionality
let's develop delete employee rest api
go to the employee controller within
employee controller
we are going to develop
delete employee rest api
delete employee
rsd api
all right just follow the steps
just create a method first public
so we are going to return
a deleted employee with status
message right for that just type
just return a map as a response
just give key as
string and value as
boolean
and let's your method name as
delete
employee
and let's pass
id as method argument
long id
and let's use add the rate delete
mapping rotation so this method will
handle or delete http request for that
we are going to use address delete
mapping annotation
and let's go and let's configure
the rest endpoint url
employees slash
id as a path variable and now we are
going to map this id with the java
variable right that is a long type for
that we are going to use at the rate
path variable annotation
it's pretty simple so in order to delete
the employee first we need to get a
existing
employee with id right
so let me reuse this code
so first we will retrieve a employee
with the id
if employee with this particular id is
not existing database then we simply
throw the resource not one exception
it's pretty simple again we just simply
pass
the employee object to the delete method
so here we're going to use
the employee repository
and we're going to call
delete method and we pass import object
to the delete method so this will return
this will delete a particular employee
and look at here the return type delete
method it is a wide
okay
now what we'll do we'll simply create a
map object to simply return
like a message deleted as a true
key as a string and value as
boolean
so we need to notify to the client
uh something like the delete record is
deleted successfully right for that we
are going to just written
deleted as true or false
okay
and just give
reference
as a response and this is
acorsa hash map
response
dot put so let's put our entry here
so we're gonna say key as
deleted
the response as uh the value
as true
okay
and return
response entity
dot
okay
and just in a body just pass
a response
so again
we have to specify
response entity as a return type here
all right that is pretty much what we
have done
let me stop the server
we have retrieved a employee with id
particular id from the database if
record is not exist then we simply throw
the resource not found exception
and we have called a delete method of
employee repository and we pass
employee object to the delete method
this will delete a
you know employee and delete method does
not return anything so we simply create
a map
with a entry as deleted through and we
simply return that
map to the client
it's pretty simple rest api
now let's start our springboot project
and let us test
delete employer hdpi using postman rest
client
alright guys our application is up and
running on embedded tomcat server on
port 8080
now
we will delete a particular employee let
me show you
uh here in our mysql workbench so look
at here we have four records in a table
so we are going to delete
or record one uh
record with id one okay we're going to
delete this particular record
go back to the post manage client and go
to the new tab here and just type
localhost
slash 8080 slash api
and we are going to
call or delete rest api for that we are
going to choose a delete http method
here
and we are going to delete uh required
with id1 so lets pass one here as a path
variable and hit send button
so look at here the status 200 and
the record is successfully deleted and
we got deleted true as a response
let's verify it in a database
so let me quickly run this query select
query and look at here a particular
record is successfully deleted from the
table
let's
delete one more record so we are going
to delete a record with id2
so let's go back to the post manager
client and just pass to here
and hit send button
yeah here we go
we got a success response let's verify
let's execute select statement here we
go the record is deleted successfully
alright that is pretty much about delete
employee rest api we have successfully
developed delete
employee rest api and we have tested it
using postman arrest client
in previous video we have created delete
employee rest api in this video we are
going to
implement a daily temporary
functionality in angular application and
basically we consume delete employer
hdpi in our angular application
so in a employee list page
we add
a delete button in actions column once
we click on delete button it will make
our http call to delete a particular
employee from the database
well let's go and let's first add a
delete button
to employees list page here inside
actions column
and then
once we click on delete button it should
make a delete employer hdpa call
let's head over to the
visual studio code id
and go to the employees component.html
and here we're gonna add a button
so we have already added a button that
is update buttons similar to that
let's add a button that is delete button
and let's bind a click event to this
button
and here we have event handler name that
is
delete employee and within a parenthesis
we need to pass id that is employee id
and then add some bootstrap css classes
like
button
and then button
hyphen danger
give name to the button like delete
here remove this hyphen
so this class is different and button
hyphen danger class is different
and also add some inline
style here that is margin left 10
and let's
save the file and let's go back to the
browser so look at here now it's looking
good right
so look at here the putter uh you know
height is quite high so let me
reduce the height of the
putter so go to the styles.css
and this is the height is 70 pixel let's
go and let's give
all right and let's save the file and
let's go back to browser
yeah here we go the height of the footer
is reduced for now and it looks good
right
now once we click on delete button it
should make a rest api call right for
that let's go ahead and let's write a
rest client code to make a sdpa call
so this uh delete event handler we're
gonna define in a employees component
here
it expects id
of type number
well
so first we're gonna make a rest api
call for that we are going to write a
rest client code
so inside employee service we write the
rest client code right here
so first write a
rest client code which make a delete
employees api so let's go ahead and
let's
create a method like delete employee
and then pass id to this method like
id colon number
followed by colon and then observable
and you can pass object as a type
and then simply return
this dot
http client
followed by call delete method so we are
making a delete http request so let's
call delete
and backstick
dollar within a curly braces
just call the base url
and followed by slash
dollar and within a curly basis just
pass the id
it's pretty simple right
and save the file
and let's use this delete employee
method inside employees component
so this is the delete event you know
event handler right so this we have
already bind in
a button in employee list component here
so once we click on this button
delete button it will call delete
employee event handler and this delete
employment handler we have defined in
employees component
inside a delete empire event handler
we're gonna use
this dot
employee service and we call a delete
employee
method and just we pass the id
and then we subscribe to this method as
it returns observable
and we can handle responses
synchronously
and handle the data here response data
like this
so after successful deletion
we're gonna navigate to the
list employees page right for that i'm
going to call
get employees
method
it's pretty
simple all right and this data we can
simply
log here
all right
now let's go and let's test our daily
template functionality from the
browser
let's save all the files and let's go
back to the browser
and let's go ahead and let's delete one
of the employee
let's say prabhas
so hit delete button
yeah so probably employee is
successfully deleted let me delete one
more employee
let me delete this ram employee
yeah so ram employee is also
successfully deleted let me delete one
more employee john yeah here we go
it means that our delete employee
functionality is working as expected
all right guys so far we have
implemented create employee list
employee update employee and delete
employee
in next video
we'll implement weave employee details
functionality
alright guys so far we have implemented
four functionalities
employee list add employee
update employee and delete employee
in this video we're gonna implement view
employee details functionality so
basically we add view button in actions
column
once we click on v button
it will navigate to the vmware details
page over there we can able to see a
particular employee details
all right
let's head over to the vs code id and
let's quickly create a view empire
details component and let's design a
vmware component template to show a
particular employee details
all right let's head over to the vs code
id
inside integrated terminal
make sure that you are in a root folder
of our application that is angular
hyphen front end
and just enter angular cli command
ng followed by g g for generate c for
component followed by a name of the
component let's say
employee details
hit enter
so this command
created four files and
it also updated app models
file
all right so if you expand
app folder inside app folder you can see
employee details folder is created
within amp details four files are
generated
and also
app model
is also you know updated with newly
created component
in declarations array
so whenever we create a component using
angular cli angular cli automatically
configure a component for that
particular model so in our application
we have only one model that is app model
all right
now let's go ahead and let's configure a
route for employee details component
go to the app routing model and here
we're gonna create a javascript object
within a route array and we configure
route for
employed it as component
let's create a javascript object
with property path
and let's give path as
employee
details
and we need to get a idea right idea of
particular employee
so we're going to show a particular
employee details right for that we're
going to need id of that particular
employee
and then
corresponding we define corresponding
component here that is
employee details component
that's it guys
it's very simple
so once we configure route next we
create a view button inside a employee
list
template
let's head over to the employee list
folder within employees folder we have
employee employees component template
and here we have a table right within a
table we have actions column
and within access column
we have already defined update and
delete button so along with these
buttons we'll also create one more
button that is
wave button
let me copy this existing delete button
and paste it here
and let me change it accordingly let's
give button name as
view
and let's change
our event handler
name here so this is
the on click
event
handler and here we're gonna change the
event handler name
something like
employee details
pretty simple
and once we click on this v button
this event handler will get called and
let's go and let's define this event
handler
in
invalid component
employ details
and then we need to get the id right
id of type number
and then
once we click on view button we should
be able to navigate to the vmware
details page right
for that we're going to use a route and
we have already defined a route
in one of the previous video for
uh you know for update operation let me
just copy the existing line of code
paste it here
and let me change the route name
right name route name we have the
employee details right
employee
details
it's very simple so this is the route
path we have defined
in app model
app routing module this is
and this is the id
and that id we pass it here
all right great
now let's save the file and let's head
over to the browser
and look at here view button is added
let me change the bootstrap css
class for view button
so instead of danger
let's say info and save the file let's
go back to browser
yeah
so once we click on
view button we should navigate to the
we employ details page
all right and look at here the url
so this is the path we have configured
in
app routing model right and this is the
id of that particular employee
well now what we will do we will design
a vampire details page and we'll make
our sdpa call and we pass this id to the
rest api rest api will return a employee
object of this particular id and will
populate the template object
on this page
alright great
go to the employee details component and
let's go and let's define a properties
inside a component that is id of type
number
and then
define employee property
of type
employee typescript class
now inside a component we need to
retrieve id right id of that particular
employee for example so look at here
this is the url and we need to get this
id
inside a component
for that we are going to use route
so in one of the previous video uh i
have shown you how to use activity route
to get this id
so similarly let's go and let's use
activated route to get this id from the
route
let's inject
activated route in this component
activity route
and using route we can
get the id
from the route
id equals to
this dot id equals to
route
and then
snapshot
and then params
and here we can pass the id
so this will give you the id of that
particular route
okay
so once we got the id we can pass this
id to the rest api and the sdp will
return our employee object updates
particular ide
so within an employee service we have
already created get employee by idsd
method right which will internally make
get get employee by id rest api let's go
and let's call this method to get a
particular employee
by ide
all right let's go let's inject
employees service
in employee details component
then a constructor
private
employee service
learning by service
now let's use employee service
here
so first we're gonna define
the empire object right
new and then apply
and here let's use this dot
empire service and then call the method
get your club id and let's pass the id
here
and this method returns
observable so let's use a subscribe
method to subscribe to the observable
and inside this
subscribe method we can handle the
response this is our basically our
circular response
now let's assign a response of the rest
api to the employee object
now once we got a response
of rest api and we populate that
response
in employee
object let's go to the employee details
component template and here we're gonna
design we employ details page
let's say
header of the page
like
we employee
details something like this
and then followed by the due
now let's create one more due
let's create a label
and
this is the bold element html element
and then
let's give label name as first name
and then let's use
angular interpolation to access the
property of the component
so this is the employee
dot
first name
so this is the employee property we have
defined in a component right
empirical component and this employee
property we are going to access
in a component template like this
okay
now similarly let's go ahead and let's
display employee last name and email id
as well let me copy and paste twice here
and let me change the label
last name and here let's
change the property
employer employee dot last name
and this is
email id right email id
and this is the
email id
it's pretty simple
let's save the files and let's go back
to the browser and let's see how it
works
yeah it is working
let me go to the employee list
page
from here
if i want to see a john cena employee
details
then i can click on view button and i
can able to see
a johnson empire details here
all right
all right guys we have successfully
implemented we apply details
let me quickly add a employee here
ram
over
ramadridgeman.com
hit submit and
let's say i want to view
ram employee details then i can click on
view button
and i can see
all the details of ram employee in a
separate page and if you want to
navigate to the employee list you can
click on employee list here
all right guys we have successfully
implemented
view employee details
functionality
in this video
let's quickly have end-to-end demo of
our angular spring boot crude full stack
application
and let me recap what are the
functionality we have implemented in our
employee management application in this
series
well we have implemented employee list
ad employee update employee delete
employee and we employ
features
all right
let me
uh you know clean all the records from
the employee list i mean i will delete
all the records and let's
have into end demo
now let's go ahead and let's add a
employee to the employee list click on
add employee link
and here i'm gonna add
employee that is ramesh employee first
name parameters last name
email id
remission.gmail.com hit submit
let's go ahead and let's add one more
employee click on add employee
tab
and let's go ahead and let's add one
more employee first name john
last name cena
and john gmail.com hit submit
let's go ahead and let's add one more
employee let's say admin
last name admin email id admin at the
regime.com
yeah here we go let's go let's add one
more employee let's say ram
and then power
ram at gmail.com hit submit
great we have added four employees to
the employee list now let's go ahead and
let's update one of the employee
i am going to update
ramesh employee
click on update button
and let's
change first name from
image to
arama something like this and last name
from
uh
jada
okay and email id
from ramesh at the gmail.com to
rama gmail.com hit submit
so look at here the image employee
successfully updated
earlier the first name was ramesh now it
is updated to
ram and similarly last name and email id
also updated right
well
add employee and update employee first
functionalities are working as expected
now let's see the delete
functionality
i'm going to delete this ram employee
click on delete button yeah here we go
ram employee is successfully deleted let
me delete johnson employee click on
delete button yeah
john employs also successfully deleted
now let's go ahead and let's see the
view employee details functionality
let's say i want to view admin employee
details click on view button yeah here
we go
we can able to see
all the admin employee details in vmware
editors page well if you want to
navigate to the employee list page you
can click on employees tab over here
and if you want to see ram employee
details you can click on view button you
can able to see
all the details of this particular
employee in real employee details page
well these are the five functionalities
we have implemented in this
employee management application
well
maybe in future i will add some more
feature to our
angular springboard group for stack
application
okay
great
so i have created 25 videos on angular
spring boot crew full stack application
series and i have created a
youtube playlist for them
so if you go to the my youtube channel
and go to the playlist section here you
can able to see angular springboard
crude fullstack application playlist
if you click on
view full playlist you can able to see
here all the videos of this particular
course are listed here
so i highly recommend you guys to go to
this playlist
and you can check out all the videos to
learn how to develop
you know full stack
application using angular and spring
boot
well i have already created a github
repository on my github profile and i
have hosted source code of this angular
springboard group for stack application
and my github repository so you can go
ahead and you can check out my guitar
repository for example
so look at here this is the angular 10
spring boot crude full stack app github
repository i have created
in my github profile account
so whenever you get a you know whenever
you get any issues while implementing
angular springboard code full stack
application
you can go ahead and you can check out
my github repository over here so this
is the working code
that we have seen throughout the series
this is the working code so whenever you
struct anywhere while creating this
full stack application you can just
check out a source code of this github
repository and compare your code with
this source code and you can find
the issues well angular 10 springboard
crore full stack app repository has two
projects angular front end spring boot
back end and this is the readme file
i have provided
link of all the videos of this
series in readme file
you can also go through
each videos whenever you want you guys
can follow me on github
usually i will host source code of all
the tutorials series courses on my
github profile account
so whenever i will host source code of
any tutorials courses or series you will
get notified
well
i hope this video tutorial series is
useful for you guys
if you like this course
then subscribe to my channel
and
if you have any queries or any questions
let me know in the comment section below
so that i will try to clear your doubts
alright guys thanks for watching this
series and yeah i will see you guys in
one more new brand series
all right guys thanks for watching i'll
see you guys in next one